Phillip L. Zweig Collection on Walter Wriston MS197
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Phillip L. Zweig Collection on Walter Wriston
1900 -- 1997
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Wriston, Walter B.
Zweig, Phillip L.
MS197
12 Linear Feet 10 boxes
Arrangement
This collection is not yet processed.
Custodial History
Materials were stored at Zweig's summer home on Martha's Vineyard where they were exposed to damp conditions. Materials arrived at DCA with a strong mildew smell and most metal fasteners severely rusted. A minority of the boxes had been attended to prior to transfer and had rusted fasteners replaced with coated paperclips, but this activity was not uniformly executed.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of research materials created or compiled by Phillip Zweig during the writing of his 1996 biography of Walter B. Wriston. It includes articles, annual reports, oral histories and other documentation related to Citibank and biographical information related to Wriston and his impact at Citibank.
Biographical / Historical
Phillip L. Zweig is an award-winning financial journalist and author with a long track record writing prescient, groundbreaking articles and books on banking and finance. After breaking into print as a freelancer in the mid-1970s writing about sailing, shipping, and banking, he joined the American Banker in 1980 as a staff reporter. Less than two years later, he broke the story on the risky lending practices and wild antics of the Penn Square Bank of Oklahoma City, forcing the U. S. government to close the bank on July 5, 1982. The Penn Square failure wreaked havoc in the U. S. banking system and led to the collapse of the Seattle-First National Bank in 1983 and giant Continental Illinois a year later. For his coverage, he received the George Polk, Gerald Loeb, John Hancock, and Deadline Club awards in journalism and was cited by the U. S. Congress, the Columbia Journalism Review, and the Bank & Financial Analysts Association.
Zweig may be the only journalist whose reporting has actually forced the U. S. government to shutter a rogue financial institution, and one of a handful who has burst a market bubble. The collapse of Penn Square, together with the Mexican debt crisis, prompted the Federal Reserve to slash interest rates by five percentage points over the next several weeks, unleashing the longest bull market in history. In many respects, the Penn Square debacle set the stage for the current financial crisis. Most significantly, the 1984 rescue of Continental by the federal government gave rise to the "Too Big to Fail" doctrine, which governed the recent bailouts of Bear Stearns, Washington Mutual, Citigroup, and AIG, among others.
In 1985, Crown published "Belly Up: The Collapse of the Penn Square Bank," a national best-seller that received rave reviews from The New York Times, The Wall Street Journal, Fortune and many other publications. Reporting for the Journal, he foreshadowed the savings and loan crisis with a page one August 1985 story on risky savings and loan lending practices. In 1997, as a finance editor at Business Week, he sounded the first alarm on the "minefields" of credit default swaps, which played a pivotal role in the worst financial crisis since the Great Depression.
His 1996 biography of Walter B. Wriston, the late chairman and CEO of what is now Citigroup, was a finalist in the 1997 Financial Times/​Booz-Allen & Hamilton Global Business Books awards. Zweig also initiated and edited "The Asset Securitization Handbook," published in 1989 by Dow Jones-Irwin.
From 1999 until 2008, he worked as a media consultant and advocate for small, entrepreneurial medical device companies that for years have been seeking to reform the corrupt, anticompetitive practices of the $200 billion+ hospital group purchasing (GPO) industry.
Zweig holds a B. A. in behavioral psychology from Hamilton College and an M.B.A in management from the Baruch College Graduate School of Business. He is married and lives in New York City.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Zweig, Phillip L.; Wriston, Walter B.; Citicorp; Alumni collections; Finance
- Additional accessions, 1900 -- 1997; MS197.001; 1 Volumes
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of research materials created or compiled by Phillip Zweig during the writing of his 1996 biography of Walter B. Wriston. It includes articles, annual reports, oral histories and other documentation related to Citibank and biographical information related to Wriston and his impact at Citibank.
  Arrangement
  This series is not arranged.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - WBW/Citi articles and WBW speeches from 1976 to 1980 covering "Wriston" chapters 16-19, 1976 -- 1980; MS197-001 (Box 1)
    10 files
  - Zweig box 2, 1976 -- 1996; MS197-002 (Box 2)
    File 1: Intellectualization of Citicorp File 2: Muffle minutes File 3: Chrysler episode File 4: book excerpts File 5: BHC amendments File 6: Citi Strategy File 7: Speeches File 8 Ford/Carter Library papers File 9: Wriston Testimony File 10: Presidential libraries
  - Citibank, 1947 -- 1997; MS197-003 (Box 3)
    Citibank Annual report 1949-1997; citibank oral histories
  - Citibank, 1970 -- 1997; MS197-004 (Box 4)
    File 1: Misc citi documents, articles File 2: Labor-mgmt committee Ford Admin File 3: Latin Debt Crisis/Bill Rhodes speeches File 4: Misc Citi Articles File 5: Bank letter 1982-1983 File 6: Citi Earnings - Post WBW File 7: WBW clips - General File 8: lending eras - Hank Mueller
  - WBW documents, 1970 -- 1997; MS197-005 (Box 5)
    File 1: Article indices File 2: Key gov't documents, presidential libraries, federal reserve File 3: Key WBW documents File 4: Documents File 5: Myths and realities of credit at citibank File 6: Key WBW docs a_ If you ask me b_quotations c_ sr mgmt review 11/81 d_ citibank ethical policy File 7: Misc Biographical docs
  - Articles, 1970 -- 1997; MS197-006 (Box 6)
    File 1: Articles, Documents for Chapter 20, Citistakes File 2A: Articles, Documents for Chapter 21, Home on the Range (move to S.Dakota) File 2B: Articles, Documents for Chapter 21 File 3: Articles, Documents for Chapter 22, Wristonomics File 4A: Articles, Documents for Chapter 23 File 4B: Articles, Documents for Chapter 23 File 5: Miscellaneous WBW, Citi articles, speeches, documents
  - Articles, 1970 -- 1997; MS197-007 (Box 7)
    File 1: Fed Advisory Committee Minutes File 2: Citibank Economic Letter File 3: Key Articles Chapters 1-12 File 4: Key Articles Chapters 13-18 File 5: Key Articles Chapters 19-24 File 6: Key Articles Chapter 24
  - Clippings, 1970 -- 1997; MS197-008 (Box 8)
    File 1: Key Citi/WBW Clips File 2: WBW Post-Retire Clips File 3: LDC Clips File 4: Citi Clips 1984-1989 File 5: General Banking clips File 6: Citi Clips 1990-1993 File 7: John Reed clips
  - Background information, 1900 -- 1997; MS197-009 (Box 9)
    File 1: Early years File 2: WBW State Dept Archives File 3: Citi History File 4: Henry Wriston File 5: Stiff Collar Boys File 6: Shippers/Transportation File 7: Banking on Moon File 8: Cuba take-over File 9: Changing of Guard File 10: Negotiable CD File 11: Pins on Map File 12: Rocket Scientists File 13: New order File 14: Matrix Wars File 15: Back Office File 16: Crisis and confrontation
  - NYC Budget Crisis, 1960 -- 1997; MS197-010 (Box 10)
    File 1: Go Go Banking File 2: Road to Rio File 3: Liquidity File 4: Problem Banking File 5: NYC Budget Crisis clips File 6: NYC Budget Crisis Clips 1975 File 7: NYC Budget Crisis Congressional Hearings File 8: MUFLG Documents